Sheldon Krimsky Papers MS282
Tufts Archival Research Center
Sheldon Krimsky Papers
1967 -- 2021
Tufts Archival Research Center
Krimsky, Sheldon
MS282
4 Linear Feet 4 record cartons
This collection contains files related to the work of Professor Sheldon Krimsky, Lenore Stern Professor of Humanities and Social Sciences in the Tufts Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning from 1974-2022. Records relate to his teaching and his work with professional organizations, including the founding of the Council for Responsible Genetics, between 1967-2021.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series: Course records; Research notes and lectures; Council for Responsible Genetics history; Correspondence; and Meeting records and research papers.
Biographical / Historical
Professor Sheldon Krimsky (1941-2022) was the Lenore Stern Professor of Humanities and Social Sciences in the Tufts Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning from 1974 until 2022.
Sheldon Krimsky, also known as Shelly, was born on June 26, 1941, in Brooklyn, New York, and died April 23, 2022, in Cambridge, Massachusetts. Professor Krimsky held a B.S. in physics and math from Brooklyn College, an M.S. in physics from Purdue University, as well as an M.A. in philosophy and a Ph.D. in the philosophy of science from Boston University. He lived between Cambridge and New York City, teaching at Tufts University for 47 years, as well as serving as a visiting professor at Columbia University, Brooklyn College, the New School, and New York University. Krimsky was a fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science and of the Hastings Center on Bioethics. Further, he served on the National Institutes of Health's National Recombinant DNA Advisory Committee, as a consultant for the Office of Technology Assessment, and was a co-founder of the Council for Responsible Genetics. He also held positions on the editorial boards of several scientific publications, and published and co-authored numerous books and articles of his own.
Professor Krimsky was married to Carolyn Boriss-Krimsky. The couple had two children, Alyssa Krimsky Clossey and Eliot Krimsky, as well as three grandchildren. Sheldon Krimsky died at the age of 80 in Cambridge, Massachusetts on April 23, 2022.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by Laurel Williams, Administrative Assistant for Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning, 2022, accession UA-2023-036.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains course records, research and lecture notes, historical files related to the Council for Responsible Genetics, correspondence, meeting records, and research papers. The bulk of the materials date from 1967 to 1992, and were produced through the work of Professor Sheldon Krimsky, Lenore Stern Professor of Humanities and Social Sciences in the Tufts Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning from 1974-2022. Krimsky was active in numerous professional organizations and was a co-founder of the Council for Responsible Genetics. Materials related to these activities are well represented in the collection.
Related Materials
Department of Urban and Environmental Policy and Planning Records, 1978 -- 2021. Tufts University. Tufts Archival Research Center. Medford, MA.
Council for Responsible Genetics Records, 1983 -- 2014. Tufts University. Tufts Archival Research Center. Medford, MA.
Appraisal
Travel reimbursement documents containing personally identifiable information were removed from the collection and securely destroyed in February 2023.
Faculty papers; Council for Responsible Genetics; Environmental policy -- Research
- Research notes and lectures, circa 1971 -- 2017; MS282.000225; 1 Linear Feet
  Conditions Governing Access
  University records are closed for 20 years from the date of creation. Records older than 20 years that do not pertain to student education, staff and faculty employment and Board of Trustees records are open for research.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in received order.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains research notes and transcripts of lectures delivered by Professor Krimsky. The materials date from approximately 1971 to 2017.
  - Anarchism, circa 1971; MS282.000226 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Open for research.
  - Anarchism and the environment, 1976 -- 1988; MS282.000227 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Source of pandemic, 2020; MS282.000228 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    20 years from date of creation.
  - Understanding DNA Ancestry, 2020; MS282.000229 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - UEP appointment, 1977; MS282.000230 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Talks (1 of 2), circa 1980 -- 2001; MS282.000231 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Tufts talk COI, 2009 -- 2012; MS282.000232 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Research notebooks 1 of 2, circa 2018; MS282.000233 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Research notebooks 2 of 2, circa 2015 -- 2017; MS282.000234 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Lecture on cultural aspects of the environmental crisis audio recording, 1988; MS282.000235 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1986 -- 1989; MS282.000236; 2 Digital Object(s) 2 5.25 inch floppy disks (Box Shared Digital Media 1)
  - DOW Chemical Company allegation, 2000; MS282.000237 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Testimony before the House and Senate Joint Committee on Natural Resources in Massachusetts, 2001; MS282.000238 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cambridge Scientific Advisory Committee report to city manager, 1984; MS282.000239 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Talk section 2 of 2, circa 1980 -- 2003; MS282.000240 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Council for Responsible Genetics history, 1967 -- 1994; MS282.000241; 1 Linear Feet
  This series contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
  This series contains research, administrative files, and publications related to the early development of the Council for Responsible Genetics (CRG). The materials date from 1967 to 1994.
  - Network participants, 1983 -- 1984; MS282.000242 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Network mailing list, 1985 -- 1986; MS282.000243 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - International Network on the Social Impacts of Biotechnology (INSIB), 1984 -- 1985; MS282.000244 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - INSIB guide, 1984 -- 1988; MS282.000245 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - CRG mission statement and bylaws, 1986 -- 1990; MS282.000246 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - CRG philosophy and goals, circa 1983; MS282.000247 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - News release, 1983; MS282.000248 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - British guidelines RDNA research, 1978 -- 1979; MS282.000249 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Rafi Communique, 1986 -- 1989; MS282.000250 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - INSIB guide, 1983 -- 1986; MS282.000251 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Coalition for Responsible Genetic Research (1 of 2), 1977 -- 1978; MS282.000252 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Coalition for Responsible Genetic Research (2 of 2), 1977 -- 1978; MS282.000253 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - CRG financial report, 1986 -- 1987; MS282.000254 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    75 years from date of creation.
  - Budget, 1983 -- 1984; MS282.000255 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - CRG phone contacts, circa 1993; MS282.000256 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Rifkin suit Dugway Proving Grounds, 1967 -- 1985; MS282.000257 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - RDNA correspondence, 1979; MS282.000258 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Executive committee business, 1983 -- 1988; MS282.000259 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - CRG contracts BW book, 1986 -- 1991; MS282.000260 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - CRG executive council, 1988; MS282.000261 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - CRG book BW, 1989 -- 1990; MS282.000262 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Conference on Commercial Biotechnology, 1993; MS282.000263 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - F.A.S, 1976; MS282.000264 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Coalition for Responsible Genetic Research, 1978 -- 1981; MS282.000265 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Study panels, 1983 -- 1984; MS282.000266 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - CRG executive meeting, 1988; MS282.000267 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Army Biological Defense Research Program, 1984 -- 1988; MS282.000268 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Biotechnology industry, 1993 -- 1994; MS282.000269 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Universite du Quebec, 1993 -- 1994; MS282.000270 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Deliberate release composite articles, 1986 -- 1987; MS282.000271 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Biotech science clippings, 1983 -- 1987; MS282.000272 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Environmental release news articles, 1986 -- 1988; MS282.000273 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Journal articles concerning biotech and deliberate release, circa 1989; MS282.000274 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Correspondence, 1973 -- 1988; MS282.000275; 1 Linear Feet
  This series contains correspondence between Sheldon Krimsky and various colleagues, organizations, and personal acquaintances related to his research, publishing, speaking engagements, and a variety of other topics. The materials date from 1973 to 1988.
  - Correspondence (1 of 2), 1985 -- 1988; MS282.000276 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (2 of 2), 1983 -- 1988; MS282.000277 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Science, Technology, and Human Values (STHV) reviews, 1986; MS282.000278 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Personal letters, 1988; MS282.000279 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists review, 1984 -- 1985; MS282.000280 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - MIT archive collection RDNA, 1976 -- 1977; MS282.000281 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters, professional, 1973 -- 1974; MS282.000282 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Regulatory Environment for Science, 1986; MS282.000283 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Biotechnology conference, 1986; MS282.000284 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Boston colloquium, 1985; MS282.000285 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Unversity of New Hampshire, 1985 -- 1986; MS282.000286 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Science for the People, the new academic industrial complex in biotechnology, circa 1984; MS282.000287 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Environmental conference, Lincoln Filene, 1984 -- 1985; MS282.000288 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Suny lecture, genetic alchemy, 1983 -- 1985; MS282.000289 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Boston colloquium, soviet exchange, 1984 -- 1985; MS282.000290 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Biographies of RDNA actors, 1976; MS282.000291 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Oral history project, 1977 -- 1978; MS282.000292 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Nature review, 1985 -- 1986; MS282.000293 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - STHV research under community standards, three cases studies, 1985 -- 1986; MS282.000294 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - EEC visitors, panel discussion, 1986; MS282.000295 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Social Risk, Science and Objectivity, Arlington, 1986; MS282.000296 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Response forms and letters in STHV, 1986 -- 1987; MS282.000297 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Boston Bar Association, 1986; MS282.000298 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - STHV work to do and names, 1987; MS282.000299 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - STHV special issue, special forms, form letters, 1987; MS282.000300 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Letters sent to contributors, 1987; MS282.000301 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Themes, potential STHV issue contributors, 1987; MS282.000302 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - STHV reviews, 1987; MS282.000303 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - American scientist review, 1986 -- 1987; MS282.000304 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - AAAS, 1987; MS282.000305 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - CRLS lecture, 1986; MS282.000306 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Corporate Technology Newsletter, 1986; MS282.000307 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Deliberate release, College of Marin, 1984 -- 1986; MS282.000308 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Twentieth Century Fund, 1985 -- 1986; MS282.000309 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - German Marshall Fund, 1986; MS282.000310 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - University of Colorado talk, 1986; MS282.000311 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Shackelton workshop proceedings, Beyond Technical Problems of Intentional Release, 1985 -- 1986; MS282.000312 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Gene Splicing Enters the Environment, 1986; MS282.000313 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Simon's Rock lecture, 1986; MS282.000314 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Simmons College deliberate release, 1986; MS282.000315 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Radcliffe lecture, southern Italy fellows, 1986; MS282.000316 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Ethical culture group, 1985 -- 1987; MS282.000317 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - New Technologies Safety and Health Institute Worcester, MA, 1987; MS282.000318 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - OTA consultantship, 1986; MS282.000319 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - OTA panel, 1986 -- 1987; MS282.000320 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Boston Colloquium for the Philosophy of Science, 1986; MS282.000321 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - New Corporate Identity alternatives, 1986 -- 1987; MS282.000322 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Graduate school information, 1986; MS282.000323 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Hale and Dorr, 1987; MS282.000324 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Plough and Krimsky, Emergence of Risk Communication Studies, 1987; MS282.000325 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - April Trip, LA to SF, 1986 -- 1987; MS282.000326 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Cal State University, Stanislaus, 1987; MS282.000327 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Simon Fraser University, 1987; MS282.000328 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - AAAS and CSFR, 1987; MS282.000329 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - OTA panel, 1987; MS282.000330 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - OTA review of papers, Davis and Jasanoff, 1987; MS282.000331 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Technology and culture seminar, 1987; MS282.000332 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Eastern Research Group, 1987; MS282.000333 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - NSF proposal review, 1987; MS282.000334 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - New Technologies Safety and Health Institute, 1987; MS282.000335 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - CEM, 1987; MS282.000336 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Review, Politics and the Life Sciences, 1985 -- 1987; MS282.000337 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Environmental Professionals review, 1987; MS282.000338 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - University of Florida, 1987; MS282.000339 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Meeting records and research papers, 1985 -- 1992; MS282.000340; 1 Linear Feet
  This series contains correspondence, research project files, literature reviews, writings, and conference materials created and used by Sheldon Krimsky in his work with various scientific and professional organizations. The materials date from 1985 to 1992.
  - Summer institute, 1989; MS282.000341 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Foundation for American Communications, 1989; MS282.000342 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - University of Rochester, 1989; MS282.000343 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - AAAS, 1991; MS282.000344 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - PRIMR, conflict of interest, 1990; MS282.000345 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - ARI bioethics review, 1990 -- 1991; MS282.000346 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Nancy Anderson's class, 1990; MS282.000347 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Northeastern biotech and env, 1990; MS282.000348 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Sigma Xi, 1989 -- 1990; MS282.000349 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - ACLU, 1985 -- 1990; MS282.000350 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - American Civil Liberties Foundation, 1985 -- 1990; MS282.000351 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - NSF proposal review, 1990; MS282.000352 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - New England Environmental Network conference, 1990; MS282.000353 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Vet school biotech meetings, 1990; MS282.000354 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - United Methodist Genetic Science Taskforce, 1989; MS282.000355 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Environmental Leadership Training Institute, 1990; MS282.000356 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Jerome Scott talk, 1988 -- 1990; MS282.000357 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Parents weekend, 1990; MS282.000358 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Dubos Center, 1989 -- 1990; MS282.000359 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - K and S speakers, 1987; MS282.000360 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Politics and the Life Sciences paper, 1990; MS282.000361 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Hubbard, 1990; MS282.000362 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Summer environmental seminars, 1990; MS282.000363 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - OTA reports, 1990; MS282.000364 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - BU Law Center, 1990; MS282.000365 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - State University of New York, 1989; MS282.000366 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - NEH proposal, 1989; MS282.000367 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Human Gene Therapy journal, 1989 -- 1990; MS282.000368 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Syracuse University, 1989; MS282.000369 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - AAAS meeting, 1989 -- 1990; MS282.000370 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Rutgers meeting, 1989; MS282.000371 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - CEM conference, 1989; MS282.000372 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - New England Journal of Medicine, 1989; MS282.000373 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Crest paper draft, 1990; MS282.000374 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Quebec, 1990; MS282.000375 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Radon paper, 1990 -- 1991; MS282.000376 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Center for Constitutional Rights, 1989 -- 1992; MS282.000377 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - CSFR, 1990 -- 1991; MS282.000378 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - AAAS, 1990 -- 1991; MS282.000379 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Congressional testimony, 1989; MS282.000380 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - AAAS annual meeting abstracts, 1991; MS282.000381 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - The Environmental Professional, 1990; MS282.000382 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - RAC Testimony September 27, 1990; MS282.000383 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - CSFR meeting, 1990; MS282.000384 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Consultant, Dynamac Corporation, 1990; MS282.000385 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Library faculty study, 1990; MS282.000386 (Box 4, Folder 54)